<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "https://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
	<maintainer type="person">
		<email>lucascs@proton.me</email>
		<name>Lucas C.S.</name>
	</maintainer>
	<longdescription lang="en">
		Lemonade runs large language models locally and exposes them over an
		OpenAI-compatible HTTP API, so any client that speaks that API can talk
		to a model on the machine instead of a hosted service. It ships two
		programs: lemond, the server daemon, and lemonade, the command line
		client used to pull, run, benchmark and manage models.

		The inference backends themselves — llama.cpp, whisper.cpp, vLLM, ONNX
		Runtime GenAI, Ryzen AI (the AMD NPU stack), stable-diffusion.cpp,
		Kokoro and the others — are not compiled into this package. lemond
		knows about each of them through a registry compiled into the binary
		and downloads the matching prebuilt backend at runtime, picking one
		suited to the hardware it finds: NVIDIA and AMD GPUs, Intel GPUs, AMD
		NPUs or plain CPU. That is why app-arch/unzip is a runtime dependency
		and why no acceleration backend appears among the build dependencies.

		The daemon runs as the dedicated lemonade user and keeps its models and
		its config.json under /var/lib/lemonade. Both a systemd unit (system
		and user scope, installed by upstream) and an OpenRC service are
		provided.

		Not built here: the Tauri desktop shell and the AppIndicator system
		tray, which upstream builds from separate npm and cargo dependency
		sets. With USE=webapp the browser UI that lemond serves is bundled
		from a pre-populated node_modules distfile, since upstream's build
		otherwise runs npm ci and the sandbox has no network.
	</longdescription>
	<use>
		<flag name="caps">Link against <pkg>sys-libs/libcap</pkg> so lemond can pass capabilities on to the backend processes it spawns</flag>
		<flag name="webapp">Bundle the browser UI that lemond serves, using a pre-populated node_modules distfile instead of a networked npm install</flag>
	</use>
	<upstream>
		<remote-id type="github">lemonade-sdk/lemonade</remote-id>
		<bugs-to>https://github.com/lemonade-sdk/lemonade/issues</bugs-to>
		<doc>https://lemonade-server.ai/docs/</doc>
		<changelog>https://github.com/lemonade-sdk/lemonade/releases</changelog>
	</upstream>
</pkgmetadata>
