<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "https://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
	<maintainer type="person">
		<email>lucascs@proton.me</email>
		<name>Lucas C.S.</name>
	</maintainer>
	<longdescription lang="en">
		whisper.cpp is a plain C/C++ implementation of OpenAI's Whisper automatic
		speech recognition model, built on the ggml tensor library and free of
		external runtime dependencies. It transcribes and translates audio using
		quantized models in the GGML format, on CPU or with optional acceleration
		through CUDA, ROCm/HIP, Vulkan or OpenCL backends.

		The package provides whisper-cli (one-shot transcription), whisper-server
		(an HTTP server with an OpenAI-compatible endpoint), whisper-bench and
		whisper-quantize, plus the parakeet-cli and parakeet-quantize tools for
		NVIDIA's Parakeet TDT models, which upstream added alongside Whisper in the
		1.9 series. With USE=sdl2 the real-time microphone examples whisper-stream,
		whisper-command, whisper-talk-llama and whisper-lsp are built as well.

		Models are not shipped with this package and must be downloaded separately,
		typically from Hugging Face. The CPU backend is tuned through the
		architecture's CPU_FLAGS: on x86 through CPU_FLAGS_X86, and on ARM through
		CPU_FLAGS_ARM, which ggml gates at compile time via an accumulated -march
		string rather than per-feature build options.

		The ggml libraries this package builds are installed into a private
		subdirectory rather than the system libdir, because sci-ml/llama-cpp
		vendors the same ggml tree and owns those paths.

		Note that the ebuild is adapted from the istitov/stuff overlay
		(app-accessibility/whisper-cpp).
	</longdescription>
	<use>
		<flag name="blas">Build a BLAS backend against sci-libs/openblas, whose cblas interface ggml-blas requires</flag>
		<flag name="ffmpeg">Link the examples against media-video/ffmpeg so they accept audio formats other than WAV</flag>
		<flag name="hip">Build a HIP (ROCm) backend</flag>
		<flag name="opencl">Build an OpenCL backend, so far only works on Adreno and Intel GPUs</flag>
		<flag name="sdl2">Build the real-time capture examples that use media-libs/libsdl2</flag>
	</use>
	<upstream>
		<remote-id type="github">ggml-org/whisper.cpp</remote-id>
		<bugs-to>https://github.com/ggml-org/whisper.cpp/issues</bugs-to>
		<changelog>https://github.com/ggml-org/whisper.cpp/releases</changelog>
	</upstream>
</pkgmetadata>
